<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Impudency and ranterism rebuked and the Quakers sincerity vindicated from a most unjust imputation of prevarication, cast upon them by Robert Rich and R. Bacon; whose spirits are discovered in this answer, which is published for the truth sake, / by G. Roberts.</title>
            <author>Roberts, Gerard, 1621?-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182753</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789391</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789391</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172702</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91859)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172702)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2646:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Impudency and ranterism rebuked and the Quakers sincerity vindicated from a most unjust imputation of prevarication, cast upon them by Robert Rich and R. Bacon; whose spirits are discovered in this answer, which is published for the truth sake, / by G. Roberts.</title>
                  <author>Roberts, Gerard, 1621?-1703.</author>
                  <author>Hookes, Ellis, d. 1681.</author>
                  <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: G.W. [i.e. George Whitehead?].</note>
                  <note>"A postscript," p. 19-20, signed: E.H. [i.e. Ellis Hookes?].</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rich, Robert, d. 1679.</term>
               <term>Bacon, Robert, b. 1611 or 12.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172702:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Impudency and Ranteriſm REBVKED; AND THE Quakers Sincerity VINDICATED From a moſt unjuſt imputation of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication, caſt upon them by <hi>Robert Rich</hi> and <hi>R. Bacon;</hi> Whoſe Spirits are Diſcovered in this Anſwer, which is Publiſhed for the Truth Sake, By <hi>G. Roberts.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>They are grievous Revolters, walking with Slanders.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1670.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172702:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172702:2"/>
            <head>Impudency and Ranteriſm Rebuked, and the <hi>Quakers</hi> Sincerity Vindicated.</head>
            <p>AS for the Pamphlet, ſtiled Mr. <hi>Robert Rich</hi> his ſecond Letter from <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> &amp;c. which is licenced and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valged by <hi>Robert Bacon:</hi> It ſavours altogether of Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Boaſting, and Railing; and is filled with Oſtentations, Lyes, and Slanders, againſt the People called <hi>Quakers;</hi> and the Folly, Confuſion, and Ranteriſm therein is ſo obvious, that every impartial Reader may eaſily ſee it, and the ſpirit from whence it came; and therefore we ſhall need to ſay the leſs to it, but ſo much as to manifeſt this Charge true againſt the ſaid Pamphlet, and the ſpirit that gave it forth, or that owns, or ſpreads it; as alſo to clear the Truth profeſſed by the ſaid peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Envy and Out-rage of this <hi>R. Rich</hi> and <hi>R. Bacon,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaid People, is of late broken forth, on the occaſion of thirty Pounds, ſent them by R. <hi>Rich,</hi> as its ſaid in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with their Brethren (<hi>viz.</hi> other ſix Churches) as they are falſly termed by them, they being <hi>Papiſts, Epiſcopals, Presbite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Independents, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and (to which he adds) <hi>the Church of the Firſt-born</hi> [<hi>intending ſuch as</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>have no viſible Church or People</hi>] pag. 8. and the <hi>Out-caſts</hi> from among <hi>the People,</hi> called Quakers, which in plainneſs are Ranters, and ſuch like among whom he numbred the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſo called, for a Share in his vaporing donation, ſo much talked, ſcribled, and trumpet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about by the ſaid R. <hi>Rich,</hi> and his Agent R. <hi>Bacon,</hi> which in that the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſo called, could not gratifie a Whimſical, Ranting ſpirit, nor blemiſh their Reputation, by eating and drinking with the Drunken or partaking with Ranters, and ſuch like, of a <hi>Cains</hi> Sacrifice, a <hi>Balacked</hi> Reward, and a <hi>Judas</hi>'s oblation, in their not accepting of R. <hi>Rich</hi> his thirty pounds (or thirty pieces) to diſpoſe of as he ordered, but only ſome two or three, admitted of the payment of the money to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172702:3"/>
them <hi>(pro tempore)</hi> till they could have an oppertunity to return it back to the ſaid <hi>R. Rich</hi> again, not at all intending to lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a Blemiſh, as to pertake and diſpoſe (amongſt the <hi>Quakers</hi>) of ſuch a ſuperſtitious and idolatrous Gift, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a ranting boaſting ſpirit (as is the ſpirit of <hi>R. Rich</hi> and <hi>R. Bacon</hi>) however, in their Title page, they have moſt ſlanderouſly branded and defamed the ſaid People called <hi>Quakers</hi> with prevarication in the matter of thirty pounds, which was never their principle, nor intention (either in that, or any other matter.)</p>
            <p>And where <hi>R. Rich</hi> in his tenth page accuſeth us called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> with <hi>a ſpirit of Pride, Emnity,</hi> and <hi>Falſhood;</hi> for that <hi>W.B.</hi> ſhould affirm, <hi>That the thirty pounds, whicw</hi> R.R.<hi>had ordered to be given to the Poor of their People</hi> (meaning the <hi>Quakers</hi>) <hi>was not received by any of them</hi> (for they denied both him and his Gift) <hi>W.B.</hi> further explaining himſelf [as <hi>R.R.</hi> is made to lay down, what he ſaid in that caſe] namely, <hi>That they never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it</hi> (the thirty pounds) <hi>from him to that end and purpoſe, but upon this very ground only, that the Money was ſent, to be returned him.</hi> Thus far <hi>R.</hi> R. his own accompt of the caſe; now, that not any of the <hi>Poor</hi> among us had it, nor did any of us receive it, but to return it to him again is true and evident; albeit, he unjuſtly hath imputed <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Falſhood</hi> to the ſaid People in this matter.</p>
            <p>And further this R.R.impudently and falſly adds, [Note] <hi>That the ſaid money was received with a clear intent to be diſpoſed of to the Poor among them, and the three perſons</hi> (meaning J.B. A.S. G.R.) <hi>ſay the recived this Money, as from him (to beſtow upon their Poor, and yet decline their ingagement in the diſtribution, as</hi> (R.R.falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaith)</p>
            <p>For anſwer to which, and for the clearing of the Truth, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decency; and Honeſty of our Intentions in this matter, from R.R.his unjuſt and impudent Imputation of Prevarication De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and Falſhood; We do conſcientiouſly, and in the Sight of God, teſtifie again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him herein, as having injuriouſly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed us and our Intentions; for we did conſider of it before we received it, only to receive it for that end, as to return the ſame Money back again to him, and to prevent any others from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172702:3"/>
it under the Name or Colour of <hi>Quakers,</hi> thereby to ſcandalize us; for then R.R.might have boaſted herein, having boaſted already upon a I ye and falſe Ground; as believing we would diſpoſe of it according to his Order, (among our <hi>Poor</hi>) which we never intended, neither did we need it.</p>
            <p>For, Firſt, in receiving his thirty pounds, we had no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent at all as to diſpoſe of it, to the Poor among us; but to return it to <hi>Robert Rich</hi> again, as we could have opper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it was never ſaid by us (as he accuſeth us) <hi>That we received this Money to beſtow among the Poor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, We could not decline any Ingagement therein, when we were under none in that caſe, as for that end to accept of his Money or Gift (for that end) which he and his Agents have ſo loudly trumpetted abroad; he many times over in his Pamphlet, telling us of his <hi>thirty Pounds,</hi> his <hi>thirty pounds,</hi> and his diſpoſing of it, which inſtead of gaining Fame and Repute there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, hath brought Infamy and Diſgrace upon himſelf, as a Proud boaſting Phariſee, and inſulting Bravadoe; however he would clear himſelf, as not being the Cauſe of his Fooliſh (as he calls it) <hi>private Letter coming abroad;</hi> howbeit, he has ſent the noiſe of his Gift abroad, both to thoſe he calls the ſeven Churches, and others, and in making ſo much mention thereof in this laſt letter of his, as alſo his Agents and Factors have ſounded his Trumpet loud enough for him, and his Gifts.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That our intentions of returning the ſaid thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Pound to <hi>Robert Rich</hi> again, were both real and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by us; we here preſent his Receiptt which runs thus <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>December 23. 1668. <hi>Received then of</hi> John Grove <hi>Maſter of the</hi> Tryal, <hi>the ſum of Thirty Pounds, and is upon the account of</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard Roberts, Amor Stodart, <hi>and</hi> John Bolton; <hi>I ſay received by me according to the Receipt within.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Robert Rich <hi>Senior.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172702:4"/>
            <p>Now judge whether this R.R.or any of his Agents, had any cauſe or need aforehand ſo much to trumpet up the noiſe or fame of his Gifts, or have either boaſted, or reproached us about it, or yet have been ſo confident as to ſay, we received it with a clear intent to diſpoſe to the Poor among us (which is an abſolute falſhood) for after it was received, it was immediately ſealed up, on purpoſe to return him the ſame money back again, as we were intended, that no blemiſh might lie on the Truth, or us about it.</p>
            <p>And now the Reader may mark, that we are not only vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified by this R.R.and (his Agent or factor) R. <hi>Bacon,</hi> for our denying him and his Gift; but this R. <hi>Bacon</hi> hath ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Trumpet on the behalf of R.R.and his Gift or Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of money (or Earth) where, in his Preface he ſounds, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the matter in theſe words <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have waited long, and hoped much, that at length you would have made ſome acknowledgement to God, Mr.</hi> Rich, <hi>and indeed to me, whom you know unanimous with him in this late, and only ſaving Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of divine Love and Grace, exhibited by and through him irreſpectively to all</hi> (adding that) <hi>Mr.</hi> Rich <hi>hath dug open a Well among you, another and a better Diſpenſation;</hi> Comparing it to the <hi>favour</hi> which the Prodigal found: Thus far <hi>R.R.</hi> and <hi>R.B.</hi> (page 3. and 4. after he mentions the diſpoſe of the thirty pounds) adds <hi>(viz.) It being a work, which in truth, tends to the gathering and uniting of all the Seed of</hi> Jacob—<hi>into the new</hi> Jeruſalem, &amp;<hi>c.</hi> Thus far R.R.hath blaſphemouſly trumpetted up his Gift and Fame therein to his own infamy, as all impartial Readers may ſee and judge; as alſo, how blaſphemous and Idolatrous this R. <hi>B.</hi> hath ſhewed himſelf in this matter, upon <hi>Riches</hi> money, offering with theſe Epethites on it; <hi>viz. This laſt and ſaving Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of divine Love and Grace exhibited by him, a Well, a better Diſpenſation, the Prodigals favour, &amp;c.</hi> Yea, and ſuch a high one (and R.R.and R. <hi>B.</hi> ſo highly concerned in the exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereof) that R.R.by this Idolater R. <hi>B.</hi> muſt be joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed next to God in it, and R. <hi>B.</hi> (next to R.R.) whoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition runs thus; <hi>viz. You ſhould have made ſome acknowledgement to God, Mr.</hi> Rich, <hi>and inded to me, &amp;c.</hi> And for what ſhould
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172702:4"/>
we have thus highly acknowledged to this Mr. <hi>Rich</hi> (as he proudly calls him) next to God? What, for his feigned love in his hypocritical Gift of thirty Pounds, which we never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to accept, either for our own, or Friends uſe; to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie ſuch Blaſphemous Idolatrous ſpirits as yours (R.R.and R.B.) are, whoſe Idolatry, Money-Diſpenſation, and feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Love, which is now turned into Enmity, and Railing we ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny, and the Lying ſpirit, by which you, are acted; and if you come not to a better Diſpenſation then ſuch beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly ſtuff as this of R.R.that ſhews it ſelf in his Gifts of money, ſo much bragged of; we may ſay to you, You and your money, <hi>Periſh;</hi> for divine Love, which is God's Gift, and the ſaving Diſpenſation is not to be purchaſed with money, nor uniting into the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> bought with his thirty pounds; nor any Feaſt procured thereby (or your eating and drinking with Ranters, &amp;c.) procure that unity, that is in the new <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem:</hi> Neither will R.R.with his Gift of thirty Pounds (nor R. <hi>Bacon</hi> with his Trumpet to ſound it up) gather the Seed of <hi>Jacob</hi> into new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> with money; whereby R.R.exhibites his laſt diſpenſation, which R.B.falſly ſtiles that of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love and Grace; ſo that we, refuſing his money, have ſtopt <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Bacons</hi> Well, and (as they judge) hindred the gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Seed of <hi>Jacob</hi> into new <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> when as that which we have ſtopt is nothing but <hi>Balacks</hi> Gift, <hi>Balaams</hi> Wages, <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> thirty Pieces, and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> his money, (which that nature was alwayes againſt the Seed of God) which is now found in <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Bacon,</hi> as may be ſeen by their Book, as the raging Wave of the Sea, that has foamed up ſhame, and fury, and madneſs, and not a ſpark of divine Love, but a ſpirit that would murther, as after may be made appear; and R.R.and <hi>Bacon</hi> are deceived to think to over come the <hi>Quakers</hi> with Gifts; and now all People may ſee their folly (and what a madneſs they are in) who read this.</p>
            <p>Now R. <hi>Bacon,</hi> thou haſt in ſeveral things, in thy two pages in thy Preface, belyed and abuſed us, called <hi>Quakers;</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hypocritically thou calleſt us <hi>thy beloved Friends;</hi> but bely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt us, as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">Firſt, <hi>That we have rejected the only ſaving Diſpenſation of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:172702:5"/>
            <p n="2">Secondly, <hi>That we have in Pride refuſed a better Diſpenſation, and that the dread of it hath been long upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">Thirdly <hi>That we ſhew our ſelves herein contrary to all men, as the perverſe and obſtinate</hi> Jews, <hi>who rejected Jeſus, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">Fourthly, Falſe alſo is thy Propheſie, <hi>What will be the exit of us,</hi> (to wit) <hi>that of Boaſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">Fifthly, <hi>That the hour of our Judgment is now come, even as we have feared it would alſo come upon us;</hi> (this falſe inſtance follows) <hi>which accuſeth us of unchriſtian, violent, withſtanding, and rejecting that appearance of God in</hi> J.N. J.P.<hi>and many others, and laſt of all in Mr.</hi> Rich (as thou calleſt him.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> This is a very Lying &amp; Slanderous Accuſation againſt us; for we never withſtood nor rejected the appearance of God in <hi>J.N.</hi> or any elſe (much leſs violently) but the appearance of the Enemy, which vailed the appearance of God for a time, untill the appearance of God did ariſe and bring <hi>J.N.</hi> to a ſence and ſight of his loſs and fall, and to Judgment and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, wherein he in his latter dayes gave Glory to God, in judging, and in condeming that ſpirit which had darkned him and others; and the ſame antichriſtian ſpirit he gave teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt, both in <hi>R.R.</hi> and the reſt that followed and joyned with him in the hour of his temptation and darkneſs; and he was reſtored before his Deceaſe, ſo far as to vindicate the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Truth, and that he could have no fellowſhip with ſuch airy ranting ſpirits as you <hi>(R.R. R.B.)</hi> are of: Wherefore, do not proceed any further to cover your ſelves with <hi>J.N.</hi> for his ſeriouſneſs and ſence of Truth, that he was reſtored to, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth your light frothy ſpirits, and this ſpirit of oppoſition and apoſtacy in <hi>J.P.</hi> which led him to where you are, into rantiſm and falſe liberty in the World; and after the glory of it, that he did not honour the Truth nor witneſs to the appearance of God in his latter dayes; his ſpirit was not ſteadfaſt with the Lord; ſo there is no fit compariſon between <hi>J.N.</hi> (in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery to a ſence of Judgment, Repentance, and Mercy) and <hi>J.P.</hi> in his Stubbornneſs, Self-ſeparation, and Apoſtacy from Truth. And whereas <hi>R.R.</hi> in his 19th page, maliciouſly and falſly renders us in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:172702:5"/>
            <p>R.R.<hi>I have long ſeen the abomination that makes deſolate, ſtanding among the</hi> Quakers, <hi>ever ſince that time wherein</hi> G.F.<hi>did judge</hi> J.N.<hi>and invited his Friends ſo to do, without ſhewing the leaſt ground of his Cenſure, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Theſe are a Pack of notorious Lyes, and Slanders againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> and G.F.in that caſe; for many can teſtifie, and G. Fs. own Letters and Teſtimonies; alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernining <hi>J.N.</hi> and the reſt of you that applaud him in your madneſs in the time of his darkneſs and captivity, under that dark power [wherein thy ſelf <hi>(R.R.)</hi> and ſuch like, together with thoſe ſilly Women, were alſo infatuated and blinded, to the great prejudice and reproach of Truth, by your means, your mad vain carriages and behaviours towards him] that <hi>G.F.</hi> and Friends did judge nothing among you but that which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and diſhonourable to Truth; and for eternal Judgement, the ſpirit of Antichriſt, Superſtition, and Idolatry he and we judged, and <hi>G.F.</hi> ſhewed reaſon enough for it, though he did not invite his Friends, as is falſly ſaid, for they ſaw enough both in <hi>J.N.</hi> and the reſt of you, which afterwards he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and you both who perſiſt in the condemned thing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in that dark ſpirit; ſo that we need not now renew their particulers (or dark things) againſt <hi>J, N.</hi> which are condemned, dead, and buried (on his part) nor rake into ſuch old Sepulcres (that being not the work of our preſent day) for <hi>J.N.</hi> with ſome others (that had been beguiled) did ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficienly judge and condemn that dark ſpirit, that led into thoſe extravigancies; and he gave divers ample and publique Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies both in words and writings for the clearing of the Truth, and ſatisfaction of the Righteous, who felt Life and Vertue from God in his Teſtimonies, againſt that dark ſpirit and power which leads into Ranteriſm and Idolatry, wherein thou and <hi>R.B.</hi> do yet perſiſt; ſo that <hi>J.N.</hi> his Teſtimonies for God and his Truth do live and are on record againſt you and your abomination to your condemnation; ſo he hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you reaſon enough in his Teſtimonies of condemnation above ten years ago, againſt thoſe things which he was in (who after repented) but you ſtill live in them without repentance, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deming your Abominations.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:172702:6"/>
            <p>And <hi>Robert Rich,</hi> Did not <hi>J.N.</hi> ſee and judge that light frothy life thou liveſt in before his publique Recantation? do not cover thy ſelf with thy hypocritical pretence of <hi>J.N.</hi> for he ſhall riſe up in Judgment againſt thee.</p>
            <p>And on what account ſayeſt thou? <hi>That neither haſt thou ſeen many among us</hi> (<hi>beſides</hi> J.N.<hi>and</hi> J.P.) <hi>who by their fellowſhip with Chriſt in his death have denied themſelves, and made themſelves of no reputation, page</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>Herein thou haſt not dealt plainly, nor told us wherein their fellowſhip with Chriſt, and making themſelves of no reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſted beyond all others of us; and thou wrongeſt <hi>J.N.</hi> in joyning <hi>J.P.</hi> with him; for did <hi>J.P.</hi> ſhew ſuch fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with Chriſt in his death? or ſo debaſe himſelf to be of no reputation in his oppoſition to Friends, his ſingularity and ſelf-ſeparation, when they could not ſet him up (as he would have been) and in his turning into the World, tis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and preferment in <hi>Jameca,</hi> whoſe way and end is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently known there? And art thou following the example of ſuch as have fellowſhip with Chriſt in his Death, or make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of no Reputation in thy ranting light ſpirit, and in thy trumpeting up thy Gifts? Let all ſober Readers judge of thee herein.</p>
            <p>And now, whereas thou calleſt thy thirty Pounds thy Gift of <hi>Love,</hi> and pretendeſt to that <hi>Charity,</hi> which neither ſeeth, nor knoweth, nor thinketh <hi>Evil</hi> of another; leaving <hi>all others to the Righteous Judgment of God;</hi> and tells of <hi>Humility, Love unfeigned, &amp;c.</hi> p. 10. 16.</p>
            <p>But thy pretence of Love, Charity, and Humility is turned into open outrage, belying and ſlandering us, as will farther appear by the diſcovery of thy hypocriſie in that pretence, who haſt not left others to the Judgment of God, but preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly haſt ſet thy ſelf in the ſeat of falſe Judgment, in the ſeat of Scorners, Railers, and Slanderers; for all thy pretence of <hi>Love, the higher Power, and of the Spirit of Peace and Love,</hi> p. 21.</p>
            <p>And now that the Readers may ſee the extent and fruit of thy love and charity, whether it be really ſo or nay, let them take a view of thy manner of Language and Phraſe againſt the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172702:6"/>
People called <hi>Quaker,</hi> whom thou thus revileſt and threatneſt accuſing them as followeth; <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.R.</hi> his Railing and Slandering, Curſing and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencing the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſo called.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not careing whom they ſlander, or what Lies they tell ſo as they may advance their Party and ſect.</hi> p. 11.</p>
            <p>Compares them to thoſe <hi>Bloody Perſecutors, who uſed to put the</hi> Chriſtians <hi>into Bears-Skins, that the Dogs might tear them.</hi> p. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Hypocritical, Proud, Self-righteous Generation.</hi> p. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This high and luciferian People, the</hi> Quakers, <hi>who for their ſhew and numbers have been as the Stars of Heaven, and who for their pride and emnity are now caſt down, to whom is reſerved the blackneſs of Darkneſs for ever; inſomuch that carnal Whoremongers and Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers ſhall ſooner repent and find Mercy.</hi> p. 15.</p>
            <p>Babiloniſh <hi>Garments, Spiritual Wickedneſs among that Tribe called the Miniſtry.</hi> p. 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The very name in which ye have prayed and propheſied, when inne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and in which you have caſt out Devils, and wrought Wonders, ſhall now reject you, ſaying, Depart from me ye Rulers of</hi> Sodom, <hi>and People of</hi> Gomorah, <hi>tis this ſpirit, &amp;c. That ſpirit of Wickedneſs in the Form of Righteouſneſs, the Scab of Contention and Strife will never ceaſe to divide you, till the name of</hi> Quakers <hi>become a hiſs, &amp;c.</hi> p. 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Lying, Wrathful, bitter, Perſecuting ſpirit, the King of the bottomleſs Pit ſhall ſo rend, tear, and devour you, till not one ſtone be left upon another.</hi> p. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye muſt fall</hi> with Hamon, Saul, <hi>and</hi> Herod. p. 21. Thus far <hi>R.R.</hi> with his Charity and love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Are theſe expreſſions of thy Love and Charity? And is this the fruit of thy high Diſpenſation? Haſt thou not here ſhewn what ſpirit hath acted thee, and whence thy thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Pounds were ſent? Why art thou thus outragious, and like railing <hi>Rabſheca</hi> againſt the People of God, foaming out thy own ſhame? Art thou angry that we would not be taken with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172702:7"/>
thy Bait of thirty Pounds, Alas Poor man! we rejoyce over thy Railing and Reproaches, and trample upon thy Envy and Malice, thy Charmes touch us not, thy falſe Propheſies and Sentencing us thus finally, to utter deſtruction, reach us not; neither can thy Inchantments, thy feigned Singing, nor Gifts allure us; for we are in that Power that ſtands over thy head, and thou wilt be diſappointed of the fulfilling of thy Curſes and Sentences againſt us; like thoſe that curſe where God doth bleſs; however it be the deſire of that black malicious ſpirit in thee, to have thy Threatnings come to paſs, to our deſtruction; but the Lord hath blaſted it, and will croſs its evil deſire, and wicked deſign: And we are glad for the Truths ſake, that we ſuffer Reproaches by thee and ſuch malicious ranting ſpirits; we are more glad that thou (in the ſpirit thou ſtandeſt in) haſt thus reproached and vilified us, then if thou ſhouldeſt have alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether commended us; for we ſhould think the worſe of our ſelves if thou ſhouldſt commend, and ſpeak well of us, in the ſtate thou art in.</p>
            <p>And now after thou haſt thus cruelly and finally ſentenced us (the People called <hi>Quakers</hi>) as with utter deſtruction, and the blackneſs of darkneſs for ever: The Reader may take notice, how manifeſtly thou haſt contradicted thy ſelf (as one whom madneſs and outrage hath infatuated) by what follows, where thou uſeſt theſe words to us, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>R.R.<hi>You have been and ſtill are exerciſed under fear, being bound to strict Obſervations thereby working out your Salvation with fear and trembling, all which the Son of Man alſo fulfilled in the dayes of his fleſh, as being born under the Law, learning obedience by the things he ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and thus far you ſtand with him in your earthly Teſtimony,</hi> p. 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> However thou blaſphemouſly calleſt the Teſtimony of Chriſt among us earthly, yet thou haſt confeſſed enough for us, to confute thy own falſe teſtimonies and railing before; for if we be ſuch as work out our Salvation with fear and trembling, follow the Example of the Son of Man in his obedience, and ſtand with him in our Teſtimony, we are not ſuch as before thou haſt moſt ſhamefully rendred us in thy outrage, nor to fall with ſuch utter deſtruction as thou haſt foretold, and thy confuſion, and groſs contradictory, bedlam (and Babyloniſh) ſtuff
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172702:7"/>
againſt us is as much as if thou hadſt foretold us in theſe words; <hi>(viz.)</hi> You <hi>Quakers,</hi> that work out your Salvation with fear trembling, and ſtand with the Son of Man in your Teſtimony and Obedience, you are a luciferan People, for whom is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the Blackneſs of Darkneſs for ever, carnal Whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Adulterers ſhall ſooner repent and find mercy then ye, depart from me, &amp;c. And thus hast thou moſt ſhamefully revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Followers of the Son of Man, and ſo in effect haſt thus blaſphemed againſt Chriſt, in as much as thou haſt done it to his, with thy dark confuſed ſpirit of Envy and Malice, who alſo to manifeſt what an Enemy thou art to Chriſt and his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſayeſt, <hi>That even the Innocency and Righteouſneſs of the Son, the Seed muſt be offered-up, and nailed to the Croſs;</hi> addeſt theſe Popiſh terms, <hi>viz. This may be truly called</hi> Purgatory <hi>or</hi> Limbo patrum p. 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> See how like a ranter thou haſt herein ſhewed thy ſelf, who wouldſt have the Innocency and Righteouſneſs of the Son of God crucified; whereas tis the old man which is corrupt with his deeds that muſt be crucified; but thou like a Ranter haſt both undervalued the Example, Obedience, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of the Son, and haſt prefered Whoremongers and Adulterers before ſuch as ſtand with the Son in his Teſtimony, it appears thou haſt a great deal of reſpect to Whoremongers and Adulterers, thy ſpirit having moſt affinity with ſuch, as will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appear.</p>
            <p>Again, notwithſtanding thou haſt ſo finally and cruelly ſentenced and threatned us, as before thou giveſt us theſe Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>R.R.<hi>Go humble your ſelves under the mighty hand of God, that in due time be may exalt you into the number of that Name unto which every knee muſt bow,</hi> p. 25. <hi>And to look to the Root that leads us either to do or ſuffer, and earneſtly to pray and ſeek for the beſt and moſt excellent Love and Charity, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here its again obvious, how thou haſt contradicted thy ſelf, and thy confuſion and contradiction runs thus, <hi>viz.</hi> You luciferian People, for whom is reſerved the blackneſs of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for ever, who muſt be cut down, and fall with <hi>Hammon, Saul,</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> in the pit; go you and humble your ſelves that God
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172702:8"/>
in due time may exalt you into the number of the Elect, look you to the root that leads you to do or ſuffer, and earneſtly pray, &amp;c. Do but ſee the confuſion and madneſs of this <hi>R.R.</hi> and how like a mad Bedla m he hath acted his part, one while bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exclaiming againſt us, and judging us to the pit, and for the blackneſs of darkneſs for ever; another while bids us humble our ſelves, and pray that God may exalt us, as if now there were hopes for us, when at other times he will not own there is any hopes for us; thus he hath bewrayed his own madneſs and folly, through his envy and outrage.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>(Robert)</hi> can <hi>Lucifer, Hammon, Saul,</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> look to the root to lead them, or they that are chained in darkneſs for ever, when thou ſayeſt Chriſt, the root bids them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and yet thou ſayeſt we muſt look to the root that leads us, &amp;c. Is this <hi>R.R.</hi> and <hi>R.Bs.</hi> Retorick from their higher diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Judge Reader.</p>
            <p>And now as to <hi>R.R.</hi> his dearly ſaluting and owning the Out-caſts from the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> as his brother <hi>Benjamin, Bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> p. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such as are Out-caſts from amongſt us are ſuch as have caſt themſelves out, by turning from the living Truth and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, to wit, ſuch as turn into prejudice and enmity, and ſuch as turn into corrupt Principles, tending to a falſe liberty in the fleſh, out of the fear of God, and contrary to the Truth received, and ſo into a ſpirit and principle of ranteriſm (ſuch as <hi>R.R.</hi> himſelf is turned into) and ſuch as turn into looſneſs, liberty, and ſcandalous practiſes, to the diſhonour and reproach of Truth; theſe and ſuch like are the Out-caſts that are denied by us, and are no Members of our Body, no Bone of our Bone, nor Fleſh of our Fleſh, how nearly ſoever they be related to <hi>R.R.</hi> and ſuch as he, as Members of that corrupt body; for they are none of the true Church of God, as falſly he terms them: So the whole body of Ranters, Envious perſons, Seedſmen of Strife, Drunkards, and Whoremongers, our teſtimony ſtands againſt, and over their heads what ever they have profeſſed, &amp;c. So we leave <hi>R.R.</hi> to the body which he is related, whoſe Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are of the firſt birth of death, being twice dead and pluckt up by the roots.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:172702:8"/>
            <p>Again, <hi>R.R.</hi> tells us of ſuch, <hi>As are redeemed out of the evil of all Sects, Kindreds, and People, who have no viſible Church, &amp;c.</hi> (and to ſuch he would have the diſtribution of his thirty pounds) <hi>who are under any Sect or ſort of People whatſoever,</hi> p. 7, 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply,</hi> What groſs abſurdity and contradictions are here! Are they redeemed out of the evil of all Sects, and yet under all Sects and ſorts of People? This is of not only contradiction, but exactly the Ranters Principle, who make no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the many Sorts and Sects of People, deeming them all the Church without diſtinction; and how doth he reckon, that in joyning, <hi>To dread and fear the Lord, to watch and keep to the Light,</hi> to be a hard impoſition, as p. 22.</p>
            <p>Its hard to the dark ranting ſpirit, but eaſie to them that are under Chriſt's Yoak; for his darkneſs can not endure the Light, nor his vain mind the Fear of God; And how doth he ſay the Redeemed have no viſible Church or People to ſhelter under, when in contradiction he tells of the Inhabitants of Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> the numbers of One hundred forty four Thouſands, p. 22. And that ſuch a People there are in this preſent World, even as he is, in Heaven, p. 25. And ſurely ſuch will not own <hi>R.R.</hi> with his money, nor any ſuch Ranters who deem it a hard impoſition to fear the Lord watch and keep to the Light; ſo it appears he and his Fellow-members neither fear God nor watch, nor walk in the Light: But in his confuſion he forgets himſelf; for in p. 8. tells us of owning all that fear God and love Righteouſneſs; and thus over and over he contradicts himſelf.</p>
            <p>And whereas he accuſeth <hi>W.B.</hi> (how true is a Queſtion) of ſaying, Rich, <hi>thou art a Whoremonger, haſt an Adulterous Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers Spirit, &amp;c.</hi> at which he ſeems greatly offended, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king chiefly theſe exceptions, that it is a Judgment without knowledge, or other proofs, and that Chriſt Jeſus refuſed to meddle with the Magiſtrates works, bidding us read <hi>John</hi> 8. 3. and <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 13.</p>
            <p>To which we ſay, <hi>R.R.</hi> has not in his anſwer cleared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of theſe things, which he takes as laid to his charge, but rather hath rendred himſelf ſuſpicious, at leaſt, in that he would not have us to judge Whoremongers becauſe it is the Magiſtrates work, as he ſaith, as alſo by his inſtance in that of <hi>John</hi> 8. 3.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172702:9"/>
which is concerning the woman which was taken in <hi>Adultery,</hi> and whether he doth really own that there is any ſuch thing or acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as <hi>Adultery</hi> in it ſelf (any more then his brethren the Ranters) is a Queſtion; beſides, <hi>R.R.</hi> renders himſelf the more ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the matter aforeſaid, that a little after he prefereth carnal Whoremongers &amp; Adulterers before us, as thoſe that ſhall ſooner find Mercy: Its no marvel he hath ſo much pleaded for Whoremongers, and ſuch as are of whoreiſh ſpirits, when he hath ſet himſelf ſo ſhameleſly to rail at and reproach the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent: So he is to be left to his own body, which he is a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of (as before) who are of adulterous, unclean, ranting ſpirits, whom God will judge.</p>
            <p>And when as this <hi>Rich,</hi> after he has vented forth his moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtorm of railing (and threatning us with rending, tearing, and devouring by the King of the Bottomleſs Pit) he moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly and ſcorn fully adds theſe words, p. 20. <hi>viz. Which thing tell</hi> G.F.<hi>that Foxyour King, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which we ſay, That as this <hi>Rich</hi> hath threatned us with being torn and devoured, no doubt but the Devil, and he would have it come to paſs (with his envy and venom he hath ſhewed in this, as all People may ſee) and thereupon he appeareth as the Devils Agent, as one in a murderous blood-thirſty ſpirit, as if he would inſtigate the outward Powers or Rulers to rend, tear, and devour us, like the murderous Blood-thirſty <hi>Jews,</hi> and Perſecutors, againſt Chriſt, who when their Accuſation againſt him, of being a Blaſphemer, would not take, to put him to death unjuſtly, made this his Accuſation, that he made himſelf a King, <hi>viz. The King of the</hi> Jews, and that he was an Enemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> upon which he was cruelly put to death, notwithſtanding he had plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given them account of his clearneſs of that matter, telling them, <hi>My Kingdom is not of this World;</hi> and likweiſe we anſwer on the behalf of <hi>G.F.</hi> that he, with the reſt of the faithful Servants of Chriſt among us, have ſuch reverence to Chriſt, and reſpect to his example, as alſo ſuch an innocent ſubjection to the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that are ordained of God, that a worldly Kingdom they ſeek not, neither is that our deſign to ſeek; howbeit, as <hi>G.F.</hi> and the reſt of the faithful Followers of Chriſt among us have
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172702:9"/>
known Redemtion in him, they are anointed and made by Chriſt Kings and Prieſts, not after a carnal commandment, but in the Power of an endleſs Life are made to raign over dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, envy, and wickedneſs, and over both the old Murderer <hi>R.R.</hi> and the Devil, and the Ranters, and ſuch murderous ſpirits, as ſeek to ſlay the Innocent, and to crucifie the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Righteouſneſs of the Son of God, which R.R.hath ſought to do in others as he hath in himſelf, according to his doctrine in p. 24.</p>
            <p>And now we muſt a little look back to an Accuſation of <hi>R.B.</hi> in his Preface againſt us, where he accuſeth us, That our Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is the abhorrancy certain outward Forms and Ceremonies, introduced (as he ſaith) of old by wiſer men then our ſelves, to wit, the Elders and Teachers of the People, for a Manuduction to the holy Underſtanding of the Heavenly things, whereby (he ſaith) Chriſtianity was upheld in great Unity and glory for many hundred years, till there was a ſtrife about them, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now ſeeing that <hi>R.B.</hi> hath thus juſtified thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Forms and Ceremonies, which we deny and abhor, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, or declaring what they are, and counts them a Manuduction to the holy Underſtanding, and thoſe things whereby Chriſtianity was upheld; tis therefore needful that we ſhould hint what outward Forms, and what Ceremonies they are that we abhor, That they are ſuch as are Superſtitious and Idolatrous; ſuch as contraey to the Form of Godlineſs in the Night of Apoſtacy, as Popiſh Idolatry bowing to Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, their Doctrine, <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> adoring <hi>a Piece of Bread,</hi> or their Sacrament, or Euchariſt (ſo called) as being Chriſt the Lamb of God, &amp;c. though but a Chriſt of their own making, ſuch Idolatrous and Heatheniſh Practiſes; and whatſoever Forms or Ceremonies are brought in the Apoſtacy, among pretended Chriſtians, which are upheld or impoſed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>Papiſts</hi> or others, contrary to the Example and Doctrine of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and contrary to the Diſpenſation of the Goſpel Power of Godlineſs, theſe and all ſuch Forms, Ceremonies, and Practiſes do we deny and abhor, however this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172702:10"/>
               <hi>R.B.</hi> counts thoſe outward Forms and Ceremonies which we abhor as a manuduction to the holy Underſtanding, &amp;c. (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making diſtinction which) ſee how exactly herein he hath acted the part of a Ranter; for the Ranters uſed to ſay, they own all Forms, Wayes, or Religions to be as ſo many ſteps and degrees towards Heaven, not owning any diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Truth and Error, true worſhip and falſe, nor between the true ſpirit and the falſe, but ſay, that all are acted by one Power; but the lying ſpirit doth act them to be ſure, and the Devil hath made Fools of <hi>R.R.</hi> and <hi>R.B.</hi> and the Ranters; but the Power of the Lord and his living Truth is ſet, and ſtands over all their heads, and his Seed reigns over their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; and that wicked ſpirit in <hi>Rich,</hi> who after he hath ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſhewed his Malice, and Envy, and Bloodthirſty ſpirit, often uſeth that expreſſion in the <hi>Revelation, HALLEL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JAH,</hi> but we know that ſpirit that tempted <hi>Eve</hi> and Chriſt, but Chriſt has bruiſed his head, and the pit he muſt go down into from whence he came; <hi>Lucifer</hi> is fallen, let <hi>R.R.</hi> read.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G.W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:172702:10"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>R. <hi>Rich,</hi> We have taken notice of many of thy ſlanderous falſe Predictions, and Railing, more then related in this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and have collected above forty of them diſperſt in thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Pamphlet, which we have on record, which at preſent we forbear, publiſhing.</p>
            <p>Thou art one of them that went out from us; for no doubt hadſt thou been of us, thou wouldſt have continued with us, but thou went out, that it might be made manifeſt that thou wert not of us, <hi>John</hi> 2. and ſo now calls Light darkneſs, good evil, and evil good, and now art become a wandring Star, up and down in thy imaginations, and now art become a raging Wave of the Sea, caſting up the mire and dirt, as may be ſeen in thy book; for had <hi>R.R.</hi> but Power we ſhould have heard his Bell, Book, and Candle ere now, but now being become twice dead and pluckt up by the roots; and alſo ſee his malice, rage, envy, and bloodthirſty mind againſt <hi>G.F.</hi> and all may ſee his mountain brings forth nothing but Bryars and Thorns, and out of his mouth comes Wrath, Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, Anger, Clamour, Evil-ſpeaking, and Malice; ſo the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is come upon him, <hi>The Sow is turned to the wallowing in the mire and the Dog to the vomit;</hi> any one that looks upon <hi>R.R.</hi> may ſee how the Sow is mired, and what a vomit the Dog has caſt up, but it may be ſome of his ſpirit may lick it up, eſpecially they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his gifts, hoping to get 30. l. more, ſuch as <hi>R. Bacon, But will the Fool ſay in his heart now there is no God, that blaſphems his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle and them that dwell in Heaven?</hi> and ſo thou that haſt uttered Slanders againſt thy Brethren art a Fool called by <hi>Solomon,</hi> who haſt ſhewed forth thy perverſe lips; and ſo thou who art ſo right in thy own eyes, and ſcoffeſt at them that be in the eye of Faith, art a Fool. <hi>But the lips of a Fool will ſwallow up himſelf,</hi> and ſo this is come to paſs upon thee <hi>Robert;</hi> the beginning of thy mouth is fooliſhneſs, and the end of thy talk is miſchevious madneſs, <hi>And bray a Fool in a morter and he will be never the wiſer; For anger reſts in the Breſt of a Fool;</hi> for how long has anger and fooliſhneſs reſted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172702:11"/>
in the breſt of <hi>R.R.</hi> ever ſince the dayes of <hi>J.N.</hi> even 11. or 12. years, and hath ſhut out love; and it is to be feared the envy foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs, and a lying ſpirit will guide him to his grave, &amp; what is the matter that makes <hi>R.R.</hi> to rage, becauſe the <hi>Quaker</hi> would not receive his gift of thirty pieces, which is publiſhed in two Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, and ſounded over the Nations; here is a <hi>Phariſees</hi> Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet indeed; and now becauſe he cannot therein be accepted, he appears <hi>Cain</hi> like, as if he would murder, as many that are not <hi>Quaker</hi> may ſee his expreſſions in his Book, and ſee his wicked mind, as his wicked, deviliſh, blood-thirſty words (from a blood-thirſty ſpirit) againſt <hi>G.F.</hi> his rage is ſo great, but the Lord will reward him according to his works, though for a time he may huff, and puff, and ſwell, and rage; had he been in <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezers</hi> day, he would have been a fit man to blow his fire, as now he is blowing the fire fro the true <hi>Iſraslites,</hi> with his envious ſpirit, thinking thereby to caſtthem in, but the fire will take hold of him firſt, and the true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> wil leſcape by the Power of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E.H.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
